<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publications on Snail Kites in Florida</title><link>https://example.org/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on Snail Kites in Florida</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://example.org/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Experimental Test of Preferences for an Invasive Prey by an Endangered Predator: Implications for Conservation</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2016-wilcox/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2016-wilcox/</guid><description>&lt;p>Identifying impacts of exotic species on native populations is central to ecology and conservation. Although the effects of exotic predators on native prey have received much attention, the role of exotic prey on native predators is poorly understood. Determining if native predators actively prefer invasive prey over native prey has implications for interpreting invasion impacts, identifying the presence of evolutionary traps, and predator persistence. One of the world’s most invasive species, &lt;em>Pomacea maculata&lt;/em>, has recently established in portions of the endangered Everglade snail kite’s (&lt;em>Rostrhamus sociabilis plumbeus&lt;/em>) geographic range. Although these exotic snails could provide additional prey resources, they are typically much larger than the native snail, which can lead to lower foraging success and the potential for diminished energetic benefits in comparison to native snails. Nonetheless, snail kites frequently forage on exotic snails. We used choice experiments to evaluate snail kite foraging preference in relation to exotic species and snail size. We found that snail kites do not show a preference for native or exotic snails. Rather, snail kites generally showed a preference for medium-sized snails, the sizes reflective of large native snails. These results suggest that while snail kites frequently forage on exotic snails in the wild, this behavior is likely driven simply by the abundance of exotic snails rather than snail kites preferring exotics. This lack of preference offers insights to hypotheses regarding effects of exotic species, guidance regarding habitat and invasive species management, and illustrates how native-exotic relationships can be misleading in the absence of experimental tests of such interactions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Spatio-Temporal Variation in Age Structure and Abundance of the Endangered Snail Kite: Pooling across Regions Masks a Declining and Aging Population</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2016-reichert-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2016-reichert-2/</guid><description>&lt;p>While variation in age structure over time and space has long been considered important for population dynamics and conservation, reliable estimates of such spatio-temporal variation in age structure have been elusive for wild vertebrate populations. This limitation has arisen because of problems of imperfect detection, the potential for temporary emigration impacting assessments of age structure, and limited information on age. However, identifying patterns in age structure is important for making reliable predictions of both short- and long-term dynamics of populations of conservation concern. Using a multistate superpopulation estimator, we estimated region-specific abundance and age structure (the proportion of individuals within each age class) of a highly endangered population of snail kites for two separate regions in Florida over 17 years (1997–2013). We find that in the southern region of the snail kite—a region known to be critical for the long-term persistence of the species—the population has declined significantly since 1997, and during this time, it has increasingly become dominated by older snail kites (&amp;gt; 12 years old). In contrast, in the northern region—a region historically thought to serve primarily as drought refugia—the population has increased significantly since 2007 and age structure is more evenly distributed among age classes. Given that snail kites show senescence at approximately 13 years of age, where individuals suffer higher mortality rates and lower breeding rates, these results reveal an alarming trend for the southern region. Our work illustrates the importance of accounting for spatial structure when assessing changes in abundance and age distribution and the need for monitoring of age structure in imperiled species.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Consistent scaling of population structure across landscapes despite intraspecific variation in movement and connectivity</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2016-reichert-1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2016-reichert-1/</guid><description>&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Understanding the spatial scale of population structure is fundamental to long-standing tenets of population biology, landscape ecology and conservation. Nonetheless, identifying such scales has been challenging because a key factor that influences scaling – movement among patches or local populations – is a multicausal process with substantial phenotypic and temporal variation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We resolve this problem via a novel application of network modularity. When applied to movements, modularity provides a formal description of the functional aggregation of populations and identifies potentially critical scales for ecological and evolutionary dynamics. We first test for modularity using several different types of biologically relevant movements across the entire geographic range of an endangered bird, the snail kite (&lt;em>Rostrhamus sociabilis plumbeus&lt;/em>). We then ask whether variation in movement based on (i) age, (ii) sex and (iii) time (annual, seasonal and within-season movements) influences spatial population structure (i.e. modularity) in snail kites.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We identified significant modularity in annual dispersal of snail kites (all adults, males only, females only, and juveniles only) and in within-breeding season movements of adults, yet no evidence of modularity in seasonal (non-breeding) movements. For those movements with observed modular structure, we found striking similarities in the spatial configuration of population structure, even though movement properties varied considerably among these different types of movements.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our results suggest that the emergence of modularity in population networks can be robust despite movement heterogeneity and differences in patch-based measures of connectivity. Furthermore, our comparison of the population structure and connectivity across multiple movement phases helps to identify wetland patches most critical to population connectivity at multiple spatiotemporal scales.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We argue that understanding modularity in populations may provide a robust complement to existing measures of population structure and connectivity and will help to clarify the limiting roles of movement for populations. Such information is increasingly needed for interpreting population persistence and guiding effective conservation strategies with ongoing environmental change.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></description></item><item><title>Counteracting effects of a non-native prey on the demography of a native predator culminate in positive population growth</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2016-cattau/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2016-cattau/</guid><description>&lt;p>Identifying impacts of non-native species on native populations is central to conservation and ecology. While effects of non-native predators on native prey populations have recently received much attention, impacts of introduced prey on native predator populations are less understood. Non-native prey can influence predator behavior and demography through direct and indirect pathways, yet quantitative assessments of the relative impacts of multiple, potentially counteracting, effects on native predator population growth remain scarce. Using ≈20 years of range-wide monitoring data, we tested for effects of a recently introduced, rapidly spreading non-native prey species (&lt;em>Pomacea maculata&lt;/em>) on the behavior and demography of the endangered Snail Kite (&lt;em>Rostrhamus sociabilis&lt;/em>). Previous studies found that food-handling difficulties caused by the large size of P. maculata (relative to the native &lt;em>P. paludosa&lt;/em>) can lead to energetic deficiencies in juvenile kites, suggesting the potential for evolutionary traps to occur. However, high densities of &lt;em>P. maculata&lt;/em> populations could facilitate kites by providing supplemental food resources. Contrary to prior hypotheses, we found that juvenile apparent survival increased ≈50% in wetlands invaded by non-native snails. Breeding rates and number of young fledged/successful nests were also positively associated with non-native snail presence, suggesting direct trophic benefits to kites. We found no direct effects of the invasive snail on adult survival or daily nest survival rates. Kite movements and breeding distribution closely tracked the spread of non-native snail populations. Since 2005, kites have been heavily concentrated in northern regions where non-native snails have established. This geographic shift has had hidden costs, as use of northern regions is associated with lower adult survival. Despite negative impacts to this key vital rate, matrix population modeling indicated that the multifarious effects of the non-native snail invasion on kites culminated in increased population growth rates, likely lowering short-term extinction risks. Results suggest that considering only particular components of behavior or demography may be inadequate to infer the population-dynamic importance of non-native prey on native predators, including their role in creating potential evolutionary traps. Our findings provide information pertinent to Everglades restoration, highlighting potential management trade-offs for non-native species that may aid imperiled species recovery yet disrupt other native communities.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Affinity for natal environments by dispersers impacts reproduction and explains geographical structure of a highly mobile bird</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2015-fletcher/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2015-fletcher/</guid><description>&lt;p>Understanding dispersal and habitat selection behaviours is central to many problems in ecology, evolution and conservation. One factor often hypothesized to influence habitat selection by dispersers is the natal environment experienced by juveniles. Nonetheless, evidence for the effect of natal environment on dispersing, wild vertebrates remains limited. Using 18 years of nesting and mark–resight data across an entire North American geographical range of an endangered bird, the snail kite (Rostrhamus sociabilis), we tested for natal effects on breeding-site selection by dispersers and its consequences for reproductive success and population structure. Dispersing snail kites were more likely to nest in wetlands of the same habitat type (lacustrine or palustrine) as their natal wetland, independent of dispersal distance, but this preference declined with age and if individuals were born during droughts. Importantly, dispersing kites that bred in natal-like habitats had lower nest success and productivity than kites that did not. These behaviours help explain recently described population connectivity and spatial structure across their geographical range and reveal that assortative breeding is occurring, where birds are more likely to breed with individuals born in the same wetland type as their natal habitat. Natal environments can thus have long-term and large-scale effects on populations in nature, even in highly mobile animals.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reproductive responses of the endangered snail kite to variations in prey density</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2014-cattau/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2014-cattau/</guid><description>&lt;p>Understanding how predators respond to fluctuations in prey density has important conservation and management implications, particularly for threatened and endangered specialists. However, directly linking prey densities to predator behavior and demography over broad spatial and temporal scales is rare, in part, because it can be prohibitively expensive and time-consuming to quantify prey density over large areas. We link nesting data collected by a long-term monitoring program for the endangered snail kite (&lt;em>Rostrhamus sociabilis plumbeus&lt;/em>) with 44 density estimates of its primary prey, the Florida apple snail (&lt;em>Pomacea paludosa&lt;/em>), collected by multiple, smaller-scale studies from 2002 to 2010. We found evidence that key components of kite breeding biology—nest density and the number of young fledged per successful nest—were positively related to snail density. Although previous studies have shown that densities greater than approximately 0.1–0.2 snails/m2 may be necessary to sustain profitable foraging and that capture times for individual foraging kites begin to level off as snail densities exceed approximately 0.4 snails/m2, we found continued numerical responses in snail kite reproductive parameters at greater snail densities. At occupied sites (i.e., snail-sampling sites in which ≥1 snail kite nest was present within a 2-km radius during the primary sampling period: Mar–May), the average snail density was 0.45 snails/m2 (SE = 0.12, n = 17), whereas that of unoccupied sites was 0.12 snails/m2 (SE = 0.02, n = 27). Along the snail density gradient from 0.2 to 0.4 to 1.2 snails/m2, model predictions indicated that 1) the probability of site occupancy (by nesting kites) increased from 0.48 to 0.69 to 0.90, 2) local nest abundance of occupied sites increased from 4 to 7 to 16 nests, and 3) the probability of a successful nesting attempt fledging more than 1 young increased from 0.02 to 0.07 to 0.43. We found no evidence of a snail density effect on nest survival. Understanding the differential effects of snail density on various components of snail kite breeding biology is essential to the development and implementation of management tools used for snail kite conservation and Everglades restoration. Published 2014. This article is a U.S. Government work and is in the public domain in the USA.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reconstructing historical habitat data with predictive models</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2014-zweig/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2014-zweig/</guid><description>&lt;p>Historical vegetation data are important to ecological studies, as many structuring processes operate at long time scales, from decades to centuries. Capturing the pattern of variability within a system (enough to declare a significant change from past to present) relies on correct assumptions about the temporal scale of the processes involved. Sufficient long-term data are often lacking, and current techniques have their weaknesses. To address this concern, we constructed multistate and artificial neural network models (ANN) to provide fore- and hindcast vegetation communities considered critical foraging habitat for an endangered bird, the Florida Snail Kite (Rostrhamus sociabilis). Multistate models were not able to hindcast due to our data not satisfying a detailed balance requirement for time reversibility in Markovian dynamics. Multistate models were useful for forecasting and providing environmental variables for the ANN. Results from our ANN hindcast closely mirrored the population collapse of the Snail Kite population using only environmental data to inform the model. The parallel between the two gives us confidence in the hindcasting results and their use in future demographic models.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Network modularity reveals critical scales for connectivity in ecology and evolution</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2013-fletcher/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2013-fletcher/</guid><description>&lt;p>For nearly a century, biologists have emphasized the profound importance of spatial scale for ecology, evolution and conservation. Nonetheless, objectively identifying critical scales has proven incredibly challenging. Here we extend new techniques from physics and social sciences that estimate modularity on networks to identify critical scales for movement and gene flow in animals. Using four species that vary widely in dispersal ability and include both mark-recapture and population genetic data, we identify significant modularity in three species, two of which cannot be explained by geographic distance alone. Importantly, the inclusion of modularity in connectivity and population viability assessments alters conclusions regarding patch importance to connectivity and suggests higher metapopulation viability than when ignoring this hidden spatial scale. We argue that network modularity reveals critical meso-scales that are probably common in populations, providing a powerful means of identifying fundamental scales for biology and for conservation strategies aimed at recovering imperilled species.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Extreme weather and experience influence reproduction in an endangered bird</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2012-reichert/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2012-reichert/</guid><description>&lt;p>Extreme weather events, such as droughts and heat waves, are expected to become more severe and more frequent in the coming years, and understanding their impacts on demographic rates is of increasing interest to both evolutionary ecologists and conservation practitioners. An individual&amp;rsquo;s breeding probability can be a sensitive indicator of the decision to initiate reproductive behavior under varying environmental conditions, has strong fitness consequences, and can be considered the first step in a life history trade-off between allocating resources for breeding activities or self-survival.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An artificial perch to help Snail Kites handle an exotic apple snail</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2012-pias/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2012-pias/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the United States, the Snail Kite (&lt;em>Rostrhamus sociabilis plumbeus&lt;/em>) is a federally endangered species and restricted to the wetlands of south-central Florida where the current population numbers less than 1,500. The Snail Kite is an extreme dietary specialist, previously feeding almost exclusively on one species of snail, the Florida Apple Snail (&lt;em>Pomacea paludosa&lt;/em>). Within the past decade, an exotic species of apple snail, the Island Apple Snail (&lt;em>Pomacea insularum&lt;/em>), has become established on lakes in central Florida. Island Apple Snails are larger than the native Florida Apple Snails, and Snail Kites handle the exotic snails less efficiently. Juvenile Snail Kites, in particular, have lower daily energy balances while feeding on Island Apple Snails. An inexpensive, easy-to-construct platform was developed that would provide Snail Kites with a flat, stable surface on which to extract snails. The platform has the potential to reduce the difficulties Snail Kites experience when handling exotic snails, and may benefit the Snail Kite population as a whole. Initial observations indicate that Snail Kites use the platforms frequently, and snails extracted at the platforms are larger than snails extracted at other perches.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The effect of changes in habitat conditions on the movement of juvenile Snail Kites (Rostrhamus sociabilis plumbeus)</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2012-bowling/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2012-bowling/</guid><description>&lt;p>The degradation of habitats due to human activities is a major topic of interest for the conservation and management of wild populations. There is growing evidence that the Florida Everglades ecosystem continues to suffer from habitat degradation. After a period of recovery in the 1990s, the Snail Kite &lt;em>Rostrhamus sociabilis&lt;/em> population suffered a substantial decline in 2001 and has not recovered since. Habitat degradation has been suggested as one of the primary reasons for this lack of recovery. As a consequence of the continued degradation of the Everglades, we hypothesized that this would have led to increased movement of juvenile Kites over time, as a consequence of the need to find more favourable habitat. We used multistate mark-recapture models to compare between-site movement probabilities of juvenile Snail Kites in the 1990s (1992–95; which corresponds to the period before the decline) and 2000s (2003–06; after the decline). Our analyses were based on an extensive radiotelemetry study (266 birds tracked monthly over the entire state of Florida for a total period of 6 years) and considered factors such as sex and age of marked individuals. There was evidence of increased movement of juvenile Snail Kites during the post-decline period from most of the wetland regions used historically by Kites. Higher movement rates may contribute to an increase in the probability of mortality of young individuals and could contribute to the observed declines.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Social network models predict movement and connectivity in ecological landscapes</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2011-fletcher/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2011-fletcher/</guid><description>&lt;p>Network analysis is on the rise across scientific disciplines because of its ability to reveal complex, and often emergent, patterns and dynamics. Nonetheless, a growing concern in network analysis is the use of limited data for constructing networks. This concern is strikingly relevant to ecology and conservation biology, where network analysis is used to infer connectivity across landscapes. In this context, movement among patches is the crucial parameter for interpreting connectivity but because of the difficulty of collecting reliable movement data, most network analysis proceeds with only indirect information on movement across landscapes rather than using observed movement to construct networks. Statistical models developed for social networks provide promising alternatives for landscape network construction because they can leverage limited movement information to predict linkages. Using two mark-recapture datasets on individual movement and connectivity across landscapes, we test whether commonly used network constructions for interpreting connectivity can predict actual linkages and network structure, and we contrast these approaches to social network models. We find that currently applied network constructions for assessing connectivity consistently, and substantially, overpredict actual connectivity, resulting in considerable overestimation of metapopulation lifetime. Furthermore, social network models provide accurate predictions of network structure, and can do so with remarkably limited data on movement. Social network models offer a flexible and powerful way for not only understanding the factors influencing connectivity but also for providing more reliable estimates of connectivity and metapopulation persistence in the face of limited data.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Implications of discontinuous elevation gradients on fragmentation and restoration in patterned wetlands</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2011-zweig/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2011-zweig/</guid><description>&lt;p>Large wetlands around the world face the possibility of degradation, not only from complete conversion, but also from subtle changes in their structure and function. While fragmentation and isolation of wetlands within heterogeneous landscapes has received much attention, the disruption of spatial patterns/processes within large wetland systems and the resulting fragmentation of community components are less well documented. A greater understanding of pattern/process relationships and landscape gradients, and what occurs when they are altered, could help avoid undesirable consequences of restoration actions. The objective of this study is to determine the amount of fragmentation of sawgrass ridges due to artificial impoundment of water and how that may be differentially affected by spatial position relative to north and south levees. We also introduce groundbreaking evidence of landscape-level discontinuous elevation gradients within WCA3AS by comparing generalized linear and generalized additive models. These relatively abrupt breaks in elevation may have non-linear effects on hydrology and vegetation communities and would be crucial in restoration considerations. Modeling suggests there are abrupt breaks in elevation as a function of northing (Y-coordinate). Fragmentation indices indicate that fragmentation is a function of elevation and easting (X-coordinate), and that fragmentation has increased from 1988–2002. When landscapes change and the changes are compounded by non-linear landscape variables that are described herein, the maintenance processes change with them, creating a degraded feedback loop that alters the system&amp;rsquo;s response to structuring variables and diminishes our ability to predict the effects of restoration projects or climate change. Only when these landscape variables and linkages are clearly defined can we predict the response to potential perturbations and apply the knowledge to other landscape-level wetland systems in need of future restoration.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Interactive effects of senescence and natural disturbance on the survival probabilities of Snail Kites</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2010-reichert/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2010-reichert/</guid><description>&lt;p>Individuals in wild populations face risks associated with both intrinsic (i.e. aging) and external (i.e. environmental) sources of mortality. Condition-dependent mortality occurs when there is an interaction between such factors; however, few studies have clearly demonstrated condition-dependent mortality and some have even argued that condition-dependent mortality does not occur in wild avian populations. Using large sample sizes (2084 individuals, 3746 re-sights) of individual-based longitudinal data collected over a 33 year period (1976–2008) on multiple cohorts, we used a capture–mark–recapture framework to model age-dependent survival in the snail kite &lt;em>Rostrhamus sociabilis&lt;/em> plumbeus population in Florida. Adding to the growing amount of evidence for actuarial senescence in wild populations, we found evidence of senescent declines in survival probabilities in adult kites. We also tested the hypothesis that older kites experienced condition-dependent mortality during a range-wide drought event (2000–2002). The results provide convincing evidence that the annual survival probability of senescent kites was disproportionately affected by the drought relative to the survival probability of prime-aged adults. To our knowledge, this is the first evidence of condition-dependent mortality to be demonstrated in a wild avian population, a finding which challenges recent conclusions drawn in the literature. Our study suggests that senescence and condition-dependent mortality can affect the demography of wild avian populations. Accounting for these sources of variation may be particularly important to appropriately compute estimates of population growth rate, and probabilities of quasi-extinctions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Effects of an exotic prey species on a native specialist: Example of the Snail Kite</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2010-cattau/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2010-cattau/</guid><description>&lt;p>Despite acknowledging that exotic species can exhibit tremendous influence over native populations, few case studies have clearly demonstrated the effects of exotic prey species on native predators. We examined the effects of the recently introduced island apple snail (&lt;em>Pomacea insularum&lt;/em>) on the foraging behavior and energetics of the endangered snail kite (Rostrhamus sociabilis plumbeus) in Florida. We conducted time-activity budgets: (i) on kites foraging for native Florida apple snails (&lt;em>Pomacea paludosa&lt;/em>) in major wetland units within the kites’ range that had not been invaded by the exotic island apple snail and (ii) on kites foraging for exotic apple snails in Lake Tohopekaliga, the only major wetland utilized by the snail kite that had suffered a serious invasion of &lt;em>P. insularum&lt;/em>. When foraging for &lt;em>P. insularum&lt;/em>, snail kites dropped a greater proportion of snails, and they experienced increased handling times and decreased consumption rates; however, kites foraging for &lt;em>P. insularum&lt;/em> also spent a smaller proportion of the day in flight. Estimates of net daily energy balances between kites feeding on &lt;em>P. insularum&lt;/em> versus &lt;em>P. paludosa&lt;/em> were comparable for adults, but juveniles experienced energetic deficiencies when feeding on the exotic snail. Due to this discrepancy, we hypothesize that wetlands invaded by &lt;em>P. insularum&lt;/em>, such as Lake Tohopekaliga, may function as ecological traps for the snail kite in Florida by attracting breeding adults but simultaneously depressing juvenile survival. This study highlights the conservation implications and importance of elucidating the effects that exotic species have on native specialists, especially those that are endangered, because subtle influences on behavior may have significant population consequences.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>