<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publications on Snail Kites in Florida</title><link>https://example.org/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on Snail Kites in Florida</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://example.org/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Experimental Test of Preferences for an Invasive Prey by an Endangered Predator: Implications for Conservation</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2016-experimental-test/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2016-experimental-test/</guid><description>Identifying impacts of exotic species on native populations is central to ecology and conservation. Although the effects of exotic predators on native prey have received much attention, the role of exotic prey on native predators is poorly understood. Determining if native predators actively prefer invasive prey over native prey has implications for interpreting invasion impacts, identifying the presence of evolutionary traps, and predator persistence.</description></item><item><title>Reconstructing historical habitat data with predictive models</title><link>https://example.org/publications/2014-reconstructing-historical/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.org/publications/2014-reconstructing-historical/</guid><description>Historical vegetation data are important to ecological studies, as many structuring processes operate at long time scales, from decades to centuries. Capturing the pattern of variability within a system (enough to declare a significant change from past to present) relies on correct assumptions about the temporal scale of the processes involved. Sufficient long-term data are often lacking, and current techniques have their weaknesses.</description></item></channel></rss>